# **Alex Savin**

samehome@yandex.ru, skype: sameskyperman, +7-921-3882934

## Summary

I had started as desk helper at Internet-cafe, spoke with clients, had worked at nights, was studying. After that, I was involved to the hosting industry, where learned more about system administration. Wrote work with name "Testing graphical applications" as finish step of my grade. Further, I joined small team of Java developers and configurators at company that developed SaaS solution for Vodokanal (water supply system on Saint Petersburg). There I grew up by steps: system engineer, head engineer/developer (Java), DevOps. In 2011 Yandex, the largest Russian search engine, hunted me. There I work for nowadays as software developer with responsibility for various parts of the vertical search services, such as Yandex.Auto, Yandex.Rabota, Yandex.Realty more or less on Java, Scala/Akka, C++ code base.

Administrator, tester, developer, and (my opinion) a little bit manager - nice set.

# Experience

## Senior Software Developer at Yandex. Vertikali

November 2015 - Present (3 months) Deal with software tasks on instrastructure team of vertical searches business unit. Lead 3 developers group with designing, developing and support backend for bunch of services such as billing system (monetization component) and quality assessment. Prefer reactive programming patterns and Scala/Akka/Spray technology stack.

## Software Developer at Yandex

April 2011 - November 2015 (4 years 8 months) Developing Java, Scala services for vertical search on car ads, vacancies and realty offers. In details: 2-4 mln entities (depends on service), >1000 partner feeds, fault-tolerant ETL (extract, transform, load) process include feed downloading, data sharding, unification, clusterization, index building, index update on 64 search machines (4 DC). Hadoop/HBase for statistical tasks, MySQL for analytics. Team share tasks on services for the best replaceability.

Figures: full index update over 15 min, fast search 4000rps 99.9% < 50ms, detailed search 500rps 99% < 500ms.

Technologies: Scala/Akka/Spray, Lucene, Cassandra, Hadoop/HBase, MySQL.

## **DevOps at Favor-IT**

April 2008 - April 2011 (3 years 1 month) Developing, managing and deploying software for water analysis. Full management process from workspace organization to production release: infrastructure tasks (VCS/IDE, CI, fault-tolerant network, phone support system, monitoring), hardware selection and installation (common/blade servers, RAID, SuSE linux, network), software development (Java EE, EJB, Servlets, JSP), deploy (self-developed system), products support. Lead (include hiring) personnel of infrastructure group (2 people max).

Technologies: Linux, Java EE, Tomcat, PostgreSQL, Ant.

#### **System Engineer at Favor-IT**

March 2006 - March 2008 (2 years 1 month) Managing server farm for the SaaS solution (water analisys). Figures: 2 data centers, >60 machines, >20 services (10-100 users each), SuSE Linux, RAID, fault-tolerant network. Manage emergency switch to slave services or backups (1h outage max).

### **System Engineer at BizHost**

July 2005 - December 2005 (6 months) Web hosting, mail hosting. FreeBSB-based virtual hosting with self-developed panel (PHP, MySQL), dedicated hosting. Figures: >10000 sites, 10 machines.

### Administrator at QuoVadis Internet Cafe

June 2003 - June 2005 (2 years 1 month) One of the first Internet cafe at Saint Petersburg. Speaking with clients, solve problems, printing.

## Certifications

### **Principles of Reactive Programming**

Coursera June 2015

### **Functional Programming Principles in Scala**

Coursera December 2014

#### **Machine Learning**

Coursera December 2013

## **Projects**

#### **Yandex Vertical Billing System**

December 2014 to Present, Extensible billing system for vertical services Yandex.Realty, Yandex.Auto and Yandex.Travel. Data flow is started from applying commercial products based on clicks, views or actions to offers with minimal latency and then building statistics, reports and recommendations for best valuable selling. There are some points: microservices, payment systems integration, reliable storage for events, multi-consumer and multi-product environment.

### Yandex.Realty

January 2014 to Present, Realty offers search. Tasks: commercial program integration.

Technologies: Java, Scala/Akka/Spray, MySQL, Oracle, HBase.

#### Yandex.Auto

August 2013 to September 2014, Car ad offers aggregator. Tasks: commercial program integration, clusterization by pictures from ads, statistics tasks (HBase based).

Technologies: Java, Scala/Akka/Spray, MySQL, Oracle, HBase.

#### Yandex.Rabota

April 2011 to December 2013, Russia's largest vertical job search engine aggregator, 0.5mln uniq visitors/day. Tasks: rewriting all components

include query parsing, storage, cloud base search integration, clusterization. Addition of review, salary statistics services. Tweak service to SLA limits (memory, network, caching).

Technologies: Java, MySQL, proprietary search server (C++).

Languages

Russian (native), English (Intermediate level)

Skills & Expertise

Hosting Services, SaaS, Java, Linux System Administration, Java Enterprise Edition, SQL, PostgreSQL, Search, Maven, Hadoop, Bash, Scala, Akka

Education

**Saint Petersburg State Polytechnical University** 

Master of Science, Computer Science, 2005 - 2006

**Saint Petersburg State Polytechnical University** 

Bachelor's degree, Computer Science, 1999 - 2004

**Interests** 

Electronic music, Classic movies